Lamed Daled 34, we're still, we're going to finish up מזוזה Mezuzah
and move to תפילין, Tefillin, so we just cover these things 1
2 3. We are going to first finish up from the bottom
of ל"ג ע"ב. Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet. So let's take a look
here. The גמרא Gemara is
where we left off was
ואמר
רבא,
VeAmar
Rava, it is about 12 lines before the lines get wide.
The line starts with the word העשוי. HaAssuy.
Right by that
תוספות אכסדרה.
Tosafot Achsadra. Right exactly, so a little bit across and down from
the תוספות אכסדרה. Tosafot Achsadra. Let's take a look. Line starts with
העשוי, HaAssuy, תעשה ולא מן העשוי, Ta'aseh Velo Min HaAssuy, you have
to put it in the doorpost, not have it automatically appear. And
now we say another הלכה. Halacha. ואמר רבא, VeAmar Rava, רבא Rava
says, הני פתחי שמאי, hanei pitchai shamai, these doors of בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, no I'm kidding.
These doors that are sort of desolate, או דשממה? o d'shamama?
Yes, something like that. So פליגי בה רב רחומי ואבא
יוסי...
pligi ba Rav Rechumi veAbaye
Yosei... no, did I skip a line?
פטורים מן המזוזה. Peturim min haMezuzah.
Thank you. פטורים מן המזוזה. Peturim min haMezuzah. So is exempt from
מזוזה. Mezuzah. So מאי פתחי שמאי, mai pitchai shamai, what are these
desolate doors? So פליגי בה רב רחומי ואבא יוסי. pligi ba Rav
Rechumi veAbaye Yosei. So it's a debate. חד אמר דלית להו תקרה,
Chad amar d'leisu tikra, it doesn't have a ceiling. וחד אמר דלית
להו שקופי, Ve-chad amar d'leisu shikufi, it does not have שקופי. shikufi.
Now what is the ceiling and the שקופי? shikufi? So רש"י Rashi
says ceiling literally means the what do you call it, the ceiling
that you basically have, which is a little bizarre because it has
to... meaning it's a room without a ceiling. Then how about a
room that has an arch but it doesn't have walls, but it
doesn't have a ceiling, right? But of course you know this בשעריך,
besharecha, those don't have ceilings, the שערים shearim of your gate, but
maybe if it's for a house there needs to be a room
with a ceiling. And according to that then שקופי shikufi would mean
not the ceiling but the lintel. The lintel is the horizontal at
the top of the door, that's the lintel, yes right? Okay fine.
So anyway lintel. So that's what רש"י Rashi says, taking it pretty
literally. The other reading of רש"י Rashi you know sort of assumes
that ceilings are not a problem and says that even
meaning not having ceilings is not a problem, doesn't have a תקרה
tikra means it doesn't have a lintel, and not having שקופי shikufi
means it does not have the doorposts. So different even within this
debate in the גמרא Gemara there's two ways of רש"י Rashi being
read. But the basic point here bracketing the ceiling approach is that
it's not enough that the thing is in the form of a
doorway, it actually has to have the structure of a doorway.
Meaning an arch would be a problem or not?
No I don't mean an arch, I don't mean perpendicular. I mean
that it has to have an architectural thing that's actually a
frame, not a doorway, a frame.
This is not so clear because as you know we read in
many people's homes, the passageway that goes from the living room to
the dining room or whatever it is is sort of like forms
a doorway in terms of its framing, but it does not actually
act some type of wood or frame inset into it, it's just
the way the walls end. And we put מזוזה Mezuzah on that.
I mean there's questions what exactly constitutes the right shape, you know,
let's say it ends this way and the ceiling is a little
separated, but okay, but basically do you need an actual structure? So
reading it this way the way רש"י Rashi reads it the answer
is you do need a structure. However there's another reading which is
that it's not the actual structure of a door frame but it's
the question about whether it's straight or jagged. When it says it
doesn't have, it doesn't necessarily mean that you need like some type
of a built-in wooden frame or a metal frame. What it means
is that it's not shaped evenly that way. As opposed to if
you've got like you're using stones and they're going in and out
and it does not create a smooth line on the sides or
on the top. So if you just let's look at תוספות Tosafot
for a minute and then I'll take all the questions. Look at
תוספות Tosafot דלית להו תקרה. d'leisu lei tikra. So תוספות Tosafot says
פירוש מקום שהפתח שוקף שם מלמעלה, Peirush makom shehapetach shokef sham milmala,
the place that the door would bang at top, meaning a lintel.
What does that mean? אינו שווה, Eino shaveh, it is not flat,
it's not straight. אלא האבנים מן הכיפה אבן נכנסת ואבן יוצאת. Ella
ha'avanim min hakippah, even nichneset ve'even yotzet.
Okay? But the stones that are coming from the כיפה, kippah, from
the roof, from the top of from the wall atop are jutting
in and out. Okay so here we have the question, does a
מזוזה Mezuzah need a literal frame or just the shape of a
doorway?
And that is רש"י Rashi says that the גמרא Gemara means a
frame and תוספות Tosafot says no, it just needs the right shape.
And even if there's no frame as long as the lines are
straight, you're okay. And we do put מזוזות Mezuzot in those types
of openings even without a frame.
כבתי תוספות, Kibattei Tosafot, as they say.
Yeah, like תוספות. Tosafot.
Yeah but in those times people lived in tents. Where did people
put the?
Yeah you have a tent you build...
well what do you mean in those times? In the time of
the גמרא? Gemara? In the time when they were traveling in the
wilderness?
Even today,
go
to Israel and other people, the Bedouins live in tents, where do
they put them? I'm not sure for how long the ישיבה Yeshiva
lived
in
tents.
Interesting, yeah, if it's a tent that does not have a... if
it's a tent that either is not a permanent structure, you know,
or semi-permanent, or it... right, so if it's going to be for
a couple of years and it doesn't have the shape of a
frame, if it's basically more like a diagonal, then you wouldn't have
to have a מזוזה, mezuzah, you're right. You need to have a
door frame. And here the question is, does that have to be
a structure or is it enough that it be the shape? There
was some other questions. Space.
So basically what he's also saying is whether it's on the horizontal
of a of a... Right, or the vertical vertical.
The point is
you don't need a frame.
You just
need a a shape. If it's jagged, then you do not do
it. Okay. All right. So that is very important הלכה halacha as
you can imagine. And now we move on. אמר רבה בר שילא
אמר רב חסדא אכסדרה פטורה מן המזוזה.
Amar Rabbah bar Shila amar
Rav Chisda Achsadra ptura min hamuzuzah. An אכסדרה, achsadra, which is like
what do they call... is it a portico? Is that the right
word?
I think so.
Frame... it's like some type of a... what? What's an אכסדרה? achsadra?
It's a portico, that explains... Anyway, it's like a it's a you
know, it's it's the י Yud can be like some even of
a colonnade surrounding it but it's open on one end. Court- courtyard,
it's a courtyard with walls at three ends. Open at the end
that you go into the house. Like גמרא Gemara sort of said
the ה Hey is like the... didn't it say the ה Hey
was like the אכסדרה? achsadra? So you walk into that one end
is open and then the other are surrounded maybe with columns and
then you enter into the house. Okay, so that has walls essentially
the columns are walls on three sides. Do you need a מזוזה
mezuzah for this אכסדרה? achsadra? And here becomes the following question that
it's not only the issue of the physical structure: does it have
four walls, three walls, does it have a פתח? petach? But it's
also a question about what it's how it's functioning. Something have to
be a בית דירה beit dirah although the גמרא Gemara did not
say that explicitly. It comes up in other places. That's the whole
reason why נפקא מינה בית מדרש בית כנסת nafka mina beit medrash
beit kenesset doesn't need it. It has to be a place of
living. What about is it something that serves the place of living
that is not itself a place of living? So you have that
in the אכסדרה, achsadra, in the portico. It's the way you get
into the house. You don't actually live in that space, right, but
it's the way you get into the house. And there also the
assumption is that it does need a מזוזה, mezuzah, that the גמרא's
Gemara assumption based on another גמרא Gemara it seems that it's only
דרבנן... derabbanan... well we'll get to... we'll get to why our גמרא
Gemara whatever that's for more technical things but in principle it does.
However we're however that's based on another גמרא Gemara that's only דרבנן
derabbanan because it is not itself a בית דירה, beit dirah, it
just goes into a בית דירה. beit dirah. So for example take
a look at this תוספות Tosafot and we're jumping a little ahead
but just to give you the background the last תוספות Tosafot on
the page: אכסדרה ומרפסת חייבין במזוזה.
Achsadra
u-merpeset chayavin bimezuzah.
He says וכן מה דהכא בסוכה דבי שער חייב במזוזה ולא סגי
דלא עבידי משום דהוו משום דהוי דומיא דאכסדרה vekhein mah dehakha besukkah
dvei shaar chayav bimezuzah velo sagi dela avidi mishum dehavu mishum dehavei
dumiya deachsadra ותימא veteima
in the middle of the תוספות Tosafot ומהא דיומא תניא יכול שאני
מרבה אף שער אכסדרה ומרפסת umeha deYoma tanya yakhol she-ani marbe af
sha'ar achsadra u-merpeset
maybe I would include these things that need a מזוזה, mezuzah, תלמוד
לומר בית talmud lomar bayit these are not real this is not
a real בית bayit you don't live in here. So מר בר
רב אשי אמר דהתם מדאורייתא
והכא מדרבנן. Mar bar Rav Ashi amar dehatam mid'oraita vehakha miderabbanan. Okay,
so מדאורייתא mid'oraita you don't have to have a מזוזה mezuzah on
this because you don't really live in it, מדרבנן miderabbanan you do.
Now you could also say the question is whether the thing is
judged on its own terms or whether in fact it's an adjunct
to a בית. bayit. But the principle here to understand is that
it's not just about the architectural structure, it's also about whether it's
a בית דירה beit dirah or not. So let's take a look
or whether it connects to one. So let's go back to the
גמרא Gemara one minute let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
So אמר רב חסדא אכסדרה פטורה מן המזוזה Amar Rav Chisda Achsadra
ptura min hamuzuzah so it's exempt from מזוזה mezuzah why
because of an architectural issue in principle the fact that it's an
אכסדרה achsadra no, but לפי שאין לה פצימין. lefi she-ein lah pitzimin.
It does not have פצימין pitzimin which are basically columns meaning it
doesn't have a doorframe.
Like רש"י Rashi we were saying.
Well right, the whole whole side is open. There's actually no no,
but there it's also you don't even have the shape. Okay, the
whole side is open. There's no frame, there's no doorway, there's no
nothing.
תוספות ורש"י Tosafot ve-Rashi say. Exactly.
Okay so אין לה פצימין. ein lah pitzimin. So the גמרא Gemara
says הא
אית לה פצימין חייבת? ha ita lah pitzimin chayav? One minute, that
would suggest that if it had some type of columns it would
be חייב. chayav. לחיזוק תקרה הוא דעבידי le-chizuk tikrah hu de-avidi even
if you would have put columns in the in the side of
the of this portico that you enter those columns they're to support
the ceiling. So they're not there to structure a door. Okay so
again even though the רא"ש ותוספות Rosh ve-Tosafot debate do you need
some type of an independent you know frame or is it enough
that you have the structure? Even in your home when you have
you know the shape by the walls and the ceiling the idea
is to create that sense of passageway. Okay here even if what
you have columns it would not be a passageway they would basically
be columns columns to support the ceiling. Okay so therefore why are
you saying why are you suggesting that if it had columns it
would be חייב. chayav. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar.
Here's what he really meant to say. אף על פי שיש לה
פצימין פטורה Af al pi she-yesh lah pitzimin ptura even if it
had these columns it would be exempt שאין עשויין אלא לחיזוק תקרה
she-ein asuyin ela le-chizuk tikrah they're not really there to structure a
doorway, they're only there to support the ceiling. Okay. אמר אביי חזינא
להו לאיספלידי דבי מר Amar Abaye chazina lehu le-ispalidi de-vei mar I
saw the איספלידי ispalidi I have no idea what this is some
type of an אכסדרה. achsadra. What? Esplanade.
Yeah an esplanade.
I saw the... I thought it was connected. Esplanade’s got to be
a French word, right? Where does esplanade come from? Sounds French.
Anyway, what the master’s house? Master’s house is what the article
says.
Exodra, exodras, whatever. Anyway, some type of a portico. I saw these
דבי מר debei Mar in the house of Rav and, I’m sorry,
דבי מר, debei Mar, the master’s house, דאית בהו פתימי, de'is behu
ptumei, it had, it had columns ולית להו מזוזתא veless lehu mezuzta
and it didn’t have a mezuzah. So that’s fine, that’s consistent with
what we just said. קסבר לחיזוק תקרה הוא דעבידי, kasavar lechizuk tikra
hu de'avidi, that’s doing to support the roof and it’s not doing
it to structure a doorway. So now we are finding that guess
what, in order to be חייב chayiv in a מזוזה, mezuzah, you
need a doorway. על מזוזות ביתך ובשעריך, al mezuzot beitecha u'visharecha, the
word מזוזה mezuzah does not mean the cloth, it means doorway. And
the point is that the doorway has to look like a doorway,
although we haven’t exactly spelled that out, it’s pretty clear that you
need side parts and a top. But does it have to be
some type of a built-in structure or could it just be the
way the walls are shaped? That was the debate of רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot and here we’re saying it doesn’t matter, even if
you have that shape, that has to be the function it’s meant
to serve. It just can’t happen to be accidentally having that shape,
it has to be that function. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara
goes on, מיתיבי, meisivei, they ask on this, בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת
חייבין במזוזה. beit shaar achsadra u'mirpeset chayavin be'mezuzah.
So בית שער, beit shaar, which was like a gatehouse with some
type of the house that served to as something you would pass
through to get into the house, and אכסדרה achsadra is again this
portico and a מרפסת mirpeset is a porch. All these things presumably
they would have some form of walls and roof, חייבין במזוזה, chayavin
be'mezuzah, have a mezuzah. I already mentioned to you the תוספות Tosafot
that it might mean only דרבנן de'rabbanan because these are not themselves
places you live in, they just serve houses, and that’s another factor
that we’re not mentioning here. So anyway, our question is that it
says אכסדרה achsadra is חייבת במזוזה chayevet be'mezuzah and you’ve got through
telling us that an אכסדרה achsadra does not have a doorframe and
is not חייבת במזוזה. chayevet be'mezuzah. So the גמרא Gemara says, באכסדרה
דבי רב. be'achsadra debei Rav. No, these are like, these are the
אכסדרה achsadra of the house of Rav, which we all know, somehow
the גמרא Gemara knew what that was referring to, and that somehow
served as a doorframe. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. The
גמרא Gemara says אכסדרה דבי רב כי אנדרונא מעלייא היא. achsadra debei
Rav ki indrona ma'alya hi. That is the אכסדרה achsadra of Rav’s
house is a true אנדרונא, indrona, not a very common word in
the גמרא, Gemara, but it really means nothing more than a room
or chamber. It actually appears a couple of times in the תרגום
אונקלוס Targum Onkelos when it says by יוסף, Yosef, when it says,
what was it, ויבא החדרה ויבך שמה. vayavo hachadra vayivke shama. It's
the פסוק pasuk
there, something החדרה hachadra and it says he went to the אנדרוניא
indroniya and cried there. Okay, so basically it means a chamber. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying that, what? It’s a fancy word to
mean a room.
Anyway, fancy for us. What? It’s more private as opposed to...
that could be, but the point here the גמרא Gemara is that
whatever Rav’s אכסדרה achsadra was, it really had four walls and a
doorway and a
doorframe and therefore זה לא חידוש. zeh lo chidush. What do you
mean like an אכסדרה דבי רב? achsadra debei Rav? Of course that
has four walls. That’s not telling me anything new to say that’s
חייבת במזוזה. chayevet be'mezuzah. Of course. What it could be telling you
is the point that we were saying that it’s not a place
where you actually live per se, it’s just the entrance into the
house, but the גמרא Gemara is saying that would not be a
חידוש. chidush. Let’s see the answer, then I think Dov has a
question. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says דבי רב debei Rav, כי... so
the גמרא Gemara says כי אנדרונא מעלייא היא, ki indrona ma'alya hi,
that’s a real room. No, באכסדרה רומיתא. be'achsadra rumisa. We’re talking about
a רומיתא rumisa אכסדרה, achsadra, whatever that means, Roman? I don’t know,
but anyway, I don’t know exactly what the word רומיתא rumisa means.
רש"י Rashi says what it means is, the way רש"י Rashi describes
it, a lot of windows. The way I imagine what רש"י Rashi
is saying is that it’s a type of a gazebo.
So it has... it does have an entranceway and it’s not exactly
like an אכסדרה, achsadra, it does have an entranceway, but it’s something
with a lot of windows, it feels like an אכסדרה achsadra in
the sense that it has this very open feel to it, but
it is more of a place with an entrance. Is it in
the house or is this a separate structure? We’re still outside the
house. But anyway, yes, this says an אכסדרה achsadra needs a מזוזה,
mezuzah, but it’s a special type of an אכסדרה achsadra that has
a doorway.
So a gazebo would need a מזוזה mezuzah basically?
Well, no, because there it’s just סתם stam in the middle of
a field. Here, all of these things we’re talking about, I just
used gazebo as describing the physical look of it. Here, all of
these things we’re talking about is that they’re attached to a domicile
and therefore that’s the point I said that’s not being said explicitly
is in addition to the structure, there’s a concept of בית דירה.
beit dira. So even though these things are not בית דירה beit
dira per se, but they are attached to a בית דירה. beit
dira. If you have just סתם stam some structure out in the
middle of a field that is not a בית דירה, beit dira,
that does not require a מזוזה. mezuzah. You had a question, Reb
Dov? No. Okay. So I wanted to show you what רש"י... Rashi...
I wanted to show you a cute רש"י, Rashi, the second wide
line,
whatever, last word on the line, אנדרונא, indrona, רש"י Rashi says קאמברא,
chambra, which of course is chamber, exactly.
What? Chambra, exactly. Thank you for the old French.
Okay,
maybe the דבי רב, debei Rav that it was a generic term?
Oh, that didn't think like the Kamidim, like Yudin, talking
about... Rav’s... what?
Abaye’s teacher was not Rav. Right, Abaye’s...
It
was like for students, you mean lecture hall. That could be. You
could very well be correct.
Like a generic way of...
Right, you could very well be correct.
I mean דבי רב Rav very often had that meaning. You could
very well be correct.
Yes, so Josh, what about like a garage?
We have cars where...
yeah, so that probably more like the בית שער. Beis Shaar. It’s
like this room you go into to get into the house, and
you don't need to go in actually to your house, and not
everyone...
some people actually live in their garage.
No, but I mean this thing,
you just use it for cars and, you know. So what would
how would that... it could very well be that that's a בית
שער Beis Shaar and it requires a מזוזה מדרבנן. mezuzah m'drabbanan. Yeah.
Okay, that’s a good contemporary example. I mean מרפסת mirpeset also is
not the house itself, but you know, if it’s... if it’s the...
whether there's a walled-in מרפסת. mirpeset. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, yeah I think Toby's probably right about the בי רב. bei
Rav. Okay, אמר רחבה אמר רב יהודה. amar Rechaba amar Rav Yehuda.
So Rechaba said in the name of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, three
lines down in the wide lines. אמר
רחבה אמר רב יהודה: amar Rechaba amar Rav Yehuda: בי חזיקי חייב
בשתי מזוזות. bei haziki chayav bishtei mezuzot. This בי חזיקי bei haziki
you have to have two מזוזות. mezuzot. בי חזיקי bei haziki was
basically a type of a בית שער Beis Shaar that as we'll...
well let’s see, the גמרא Gemara. will say: מאי בי חזיקי? mai
bei haziki? What is this? אמר רב סבא משמיה דרב... amar Rav
Sabba mishmei deRav... let me check that line again... פפא, רב פפא.
Papa, Rav Papa. אמר רב פפא סבא משמיה דרב: amar Rav Papa
Sabba mishmei deRav: בית שער הפתוח לחצר ובתים פתוחים לבית שער. Beis
Shaar hapatuach lechatzer ubatim petuchim leBeis Shaar. So you basically have a
חצר, chatzer, which is a... which is a courtyard, but not your
private yard, it is the courtyard over the court. You have houses
that opened up into a חצר. chatzer. Okay, so... and so basically
you have this בית שער Beis Shaar this... where it opened up
into the courtyard and the courtyard to the house. So imagine, I
don't know, you have like
all
of these homes living around the courtyard, and you have a little
בית שער Beis Shaar when somebody wants to go to your house,
they don't go straight up to the front door, they first come
from the courtyard into the בית שער, Beis Shaar, and this is...
I don’t know what this...
okay, whatever it is.
They come into the בית שער Beis Shaar and from the בית
שער, Beis Shaar, they come into your house. So the point is,
where do you need the מזוזה? mezuzah? If you see it, it
has two doors. It has the door when you're going from the
courtyard into this little room, an antechamber, and then it has from
this little room into your house. So his חידוש chiddush is it
needs two מזוזות. mezuzot. Certainly the door going into your house is
like a door to the house, and here we see the idea
that it's not the structure on its own terms, it's because of
its connectedness to the house. So because the door of this בית
שער Beis Shaar that enters your house, but how about the door
that goes from the courtyard into it? You're not... it's not yet,
you know, a house yet itself, it’s only going to get you
into the house. Nevertheless, it does need it because this ultimately is
the way... it's become an appendage, you know, an extension of the
house and this is a way into the house, so that even
the door that’s from the courtyard into the בית שער Beis Shaar
as well needs a
מזוזה.
mezuzah. Okay. So... so... where were we? So now it says like
this.
Let me just check רש"י Rashi for a second, hold on.
Yeah, רש"י... Rashi... not רש"י, Rashi, it's the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא
Gemara actually... I might have described it a little imprecisely. The גמרא
Gemara says בתים פתוחים לבית שער. batim petuchim leBeis Shaar. So
not the בית, bayit, not an individual's house. So it might be
a case where there's an open section of the courtyard where there
are no houses, and here the back section of the courtyard has
the houses, and you have your בית שער Beis Shaar here. So
you know this open section where there are no houses feeds into
the בית שער, Beis Shaar, and then the בית שער Beis Shaar
is the way you get into the section with the houses. גמרא's
Gemara language is בתים, batim, not בית. bayit. But it's the same
idea that you need the מזוזה mezuzah at both ends. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בית
שער הפתוח לגינה. Beis Shaar hapatuach legina.
Now we're going to have another בית שער, Beis Shaar, but it's
going to be less significant because it does not open into a
whole courtyard filled with houses, it only opens up into an individual
house, and not only an individual house, but like a small little
house. Okay. So בית שער הפתוח לגינה, Beis Shaar hapatuach legina, now
it's opened not into a courtyard but into a, you know, garden,
so it's a more smaller scale here, ולקייטונית. u'lekaitonit. And a קייטונית
kaitonit is like the word קטן, katan, maybe it’s פתח קטן petach
katan or something like that, but anyway, פסימותא pissomit is some small
little house. So it’s the same idea except as opposed to being
open into a large courtyard which serves a lot of houses and
then opening up into a space of many big houses, it’s opening
up into a small little house.
Area? Like a storage bin or something? Store?
No, storage would not... if you have a separate storage free-standing storage
space in your backyard or whatever that does not require a מזוזה.
mezuzah. It's not a בית דירה beis dira and it’s not directly
connected to a בית דירה. beis dira. Okay. So רבי יוסי אומר:
Rabbi Yosi omer: נידון כקייטונית. nidon kekaitonit.
It’s like an extension of this קייטונית, kaitonit, this mini house, and
therefore it requires a מזוזה. mezuzah. וחכמים אומרים: Vachachamim omrim: נידון כבית
שער. nidon keBeis Shaar.
No, it’s like a בית שער. Beis Shaar. Now of course it
usually means like a בית שער. Beis Shaar. A בית שער Beis
Shaar requires a מזוזה. mezuzah. So רש"י’s Rashi גרסא girsa or interpretation
is כאויר. ka'avir. It means it's like the בית שער Beis Shaar
is like it's serving the garden and it's not really serving the
house, and therefore it does not require a מזוזה. mezuzah.
So what is the case here again?
You have a little garden in your backyard, you have a little...
you don't have a... your real house in this garden area, you
have a little place where you, I don't know,
you... No, no, no. I've got my big house way back at
the estate there. At Tara, you know, whatever. We got the big
house. Over here in the garden, okay, we have a middle house
where the gardener sleeps let's say or whatever it might be. A
gazebo. And well but a gazebo's not really like a house, I'm
bracketing a gazebo. And we've got this little בית שער beis sha'ar
from which you get from this little gardener's house let's call it
into the garden and people actually use it. Use the בית שער,
beis sha'ar, but they don't live in the בית שער, beis sha'ar,
they live in the קיטונית. kitonis. Okay, so the question is, is
this בית שער beis sha'ar basically seen as an appendage to the
garden and therefore does not require a מזוזה mezuzah or an appendage
to the house and does require a מזוזה? mezuzah? So the implicit
thing's going on here that it's not the structure but it's function
and associated with a בית דירה. beis dirah. Okay. So רב יוסף
Rav Yosef אומר נידון כקיטונית, omer nido k'kitonis, it's like the what
you know, the little house, and it has מזוזה. mezuzah. חכמים Chachamim
אומרים נידון כבית שער. omer nido k'beis sha'ar. No, it's associated with
the garden and does not require מזוזה. mezuzah. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו,
Rav u'Shmuel d'amri taveihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both said, מגינה
לבית, mi-gina l'bayis, excuse me,
depends which direction you're going. If you're going from the garden into
the house, this little house, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחייב. kuli alma
lo piligi d'chayav. So meaning, so which door are you going through?
Remember we spoke about two doors? This בית שער, beis sha'ar, one
door opens into the garden, one door opens into the house. So
if you're going from the door that opens into the house from
the בית שער, beis sha'ar, then that's really like a door of
the house. And then it's חייב chayav in מזוזה. mezuzah. Is this
sort of clear?
It depends which way you're going. If you're going out from the
house that way, then if you're going in that way, it doesn't
matter which way you are going.
Which door is it? It's the door that connects the בית שער
beis sha'ar to the house. Right? If it's the door that connects
the בית שער beis sha'ar to the house, then of course then
it's connected to the house and it requires a מזוזה. mezuzah.
Where are we?
רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri taveihu, מגינה לבית mi-gina l'bayis
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחייב. kuli alma lo piligi d'chayav.
So the direction of garden to house, which really is a funny
way of saying it, but it means, רש"י Rashi has a couple
of explanations, but I'm doing the simplest one, the door that connects
the בית שער beis sha'ar to the house, that requires a מזוזה.
mezuzah. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? ביאת דביתא הוא, Bei d'bayis hu, that's
how you get into the house. כי פליגי מבית לגינה. Ki piligi
mi-bayis l'gina. The door that connects the house to the garden, which
really means the door that connects the בית שער beis sha'ar to
the garden. Okay, so if it's that door, מר סבר קיטונית עיקר,
mar savar kitonis ikar, that when you're sort of going, you know,
from the garden to the בית שער, beis sha'ar, the בית שער
beis sha'ar to the garden, you're focusing on that door, you're seeing
this as an appendage of the garden. It's no longer seen at
that stage it's not, it's פטור. patur. And מר סבר, mar savar,
I'm sorry, so מר סבר, mar savar, I'm sorry,
I read it out of order. מר סבר קיטונית עיקר, mar savar
kitonis ikar, קיטונית kitonis is the house. The house is עיקר, ikar,
so even there when you're going to the garden, you still see
it as an extension of the house. ומר סבר גינה עיקר. u'mar
savar gina ikar. No, for that door, we look at its connection
to the garden and we don't say it's connected to the house
and therefore it does not have a, does not have a מזוזה.
mezuzah. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Raba v'Rav Yosef d'amri taveihu, now
רבה Raba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef take a similar approach except
they're a little more מיקל. meikel. No, מבית לגינה, mi-bayis l'gina,
the door that connects the house, the בית שער beis sha'ar to
the garden, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דפטור. kuli alma lo piligi d'patur.
Everybody agrees, saying logic just being more lenient. Everybody, everybody agrees that's
exempt. When you're going from the door to the garden or the
garden to the בית שער, beis sha'ar, that's very much connected to
the garden and therefore not חייב chayav in a מזוזה. mezuzah. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? פתחה דגינה הוא. pischa d'gina hu. In that context,
it's an opening into the garden. כי פליגי מגינה לבית. Ki piligi
mi-gina l'bayis.
The door that connects the garden here but it literally means the
בית שער beis sha'ar to the house. Okay, מר סבר ביאת דביתא
הוא, mar savar bei d'bayis hu, it's a way of getting into
the house, ומר סבר כולה דעתא דגינה הוא. u'mar savar kula da'ata
d'gina hu. No, this is all, oh, even though it's connecting it,
it's seen as an extension of the garden. The way the garden
feeds into the house, but it's not seen as an opening to
the house, it's seen as an exiting from the garden. All right,
so what are you doing? You're getting into the house or you're
leaving the garden? So that's the debate. Okay, so הוא דעבידא. hu
d'avida. So אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava נקט nakat up ל"ד עמוד א'.
lamed daled amud alef. אביי ורבא דעבידי כרבה ורב יוסף. Abaye v'Rava
d'avidi k'Raba v'Rav Yosef.
So אביי Abaye and רבא Rava went like רבה Raba and רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, who was the more lenient opinion. רב יוסף Rav
Yosef was
אביי's Abaye רבי, rebi, makes sense that they went there, those were
their רבייהם. rebbeim. Okay, which is a more lenient opinion, that everybody
agrees the side opening to the garden is exempt. The only debate
is the side opening into the house. ורב
אשי v'Rav Ashi עביד כרב ושמואל avid k'Rav u'Shmuel לחומרא, l'chumra, the
more מחמיר machmir position, where it was debated that maybe even the
side of the garden needs a מזוזה. mezuzah. והלכתא כרב ושמואל לחומרא.
V'hilchasa k'Rav u'Shmuel l'chumra.
And we actually rule לחומרא, l'chumra, and once we rule לחומרא, l'chumra,
we're going to rule לחומרא l'chumra on both doors. The one in
the house, which everybody according to this that is חייב, chayav, and
the one into the garden, which we said is debated. So what
we see here is that it's not just the structure of the
פתח, pesach, but it is also the question of the function and
its connectedness to a בית bayis or בית דירה. beis dirah. To
the point where even the two doors of it, one door might
be seen as serving the garden and the other seen as serving
the house. Okay, now we continue, looking at this question about sort
of different types of things that connect houses and spaces. איתמר Itmar
was taught. לול פתוח מן הבית לעלייה. Lul patuach min ha-bayis l'aliya.
If you have a לול, lul, like a לול lul can be
thought of as like a trap door. but anyway, a funnel, no
not funnel, whatever, like a tunnel or thing that connects you from
the house to the attic. What you would have is you'd have
separate people living in the attic, right? You'd rent out your attic.
It would be this totally separate family. Now, how do you get
from the attic outside? So you have to go through the main
house, they didn't have a separate exit. Now, that's a little bit
of a problem because, you know, what about people's privacy? Right? You'd
have to, you know, if I want, you know, so if somebody
wants to go up into the attic, they just what, open up
the attic door and they're right inside? Or you know, they come
down and they're right inside a person's house? So what they did
was, sort of like they have in פרומי, frum-y, like you know,
places where after you know, in some buildings you get an elevator
that goes right into a person's apartment building. But most places you
get an elevator that goes into a little lobby space, even if
there are no other apartments on that floor, you know, it goes
into a little lobby space and then you have the door, and
that affords, that allows you to travel up but to be privacy.
So that's what they did. They would have a staircase that would
go from the ground floor to the עליה, aliya, but they would
build around the staircase walls and doors. So when you would go
up the staircase you'd be on a little landing and you'd have
to knock on the door to get into the עליה, aliya, and
the same when you came down, you'd be on a little landing
and you'd have to knock on the door. It makes a lot
of sense. Now the question is, do you put מזוזות mezuzot on
those doors? And do you put them on both of the doors?
Okay, you would think you would because they're still doors, you know,
whatever. Certainly you would think you would put it on the עליה
aliya door, that's the only way you get into the עליה. aliya.
The house is less clear because the house is like fundamentally that's
not the door of the house, the door of the house is
the outside door, and that room is not even the room of
the same person. It's you know, it's not the normal way you
get into the house or out of the house, right? It's only
for the people who live upstairs how they would get down. So
let's take a look. So it says like this: לול פתוח מן
הבית לעליה. Lul patuach min habayit l'aliya. So אמר רב הונא: Amar
Rav Huna: אם יש לו פתח אחד חייב במזוזה. im yesh lo
petach echad chayav bemezuza.
If it has one opening or just one, well let's take a
look. חייב במזוזה אחת. chayav bemezuza achat. אם יש לו ב' פתחים
חייב בשתי מזוזות. im yesh lo bet petachim chayav b'shtei mezuzot. So
however many doors, that's however many מזוזות. mezuzot. If you have only
a door at one of the landings, that gets it, but if
you have a door at both of the landings, you need two
מזוזות. mezuzot. Okay, that's pretty reasonable. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa:
שמע מינה מדרב הונא, shma mina mi'deRav Huna, so we hear from
Rav Huna: האי אנדרונא, hai androna, there's that אנדרונא androna again, a
chamber, דאית ליה ארבע בבי, d'it leh arba bavi, that has four
doors, חייב בארבע מזוזות, chayav b'arba mezuzot, need four מזוזות. mezuzot.
Okay
because here you know, you realize that the גמרא Gemara has not
been so clear on this, right? Does every single doorway you have
in your room require a מזוזה? mezuza? Maybe it's only the primary
form of ingress and egress. If you remember the גמרא Gemara before,
it spoke about you know, whoever it was, was it רב Rav,
or רבא Rava or whatever who had, רבי Rebbe who had a
little, a little private doorway that he got to the בית מדרש.
Beit Midrash. And so it didn't need a מזוזה. mezuza. So is
that because it was not used so frequently? Or was it because
it was, you know, you go by primary, only primary doors require
as opposed to non-primary doors? And maybe it was different, that was
a private door. Maybe it was different because it was private. So
here that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. We're learning from here
because the issue is not the עליה, aliya, the עליה aliya only
has one door. The issue is the main house. The main house,
this little door that connects it to the עליה aliya is by
no means the main door. It's not the way you get into
the house, it's not the way you get out of the house,
it's by no means the main door. And nevertheless, it's חייב במזוזה.
chayav bemezuza. So now we see that if you have a room
even with four doors, each door going, connecting to a different room
in the house, right? And so nevertheless, any doorway within a room
requires a מזוזה. mezuza.
Wait, how did they get in and out of the, into the
street and out of the street then?
I thought the people in the עליה... aliya... Yeah, they have to
go through the house. But for the people who live in the
house, right? This door to the עליה aliya is a very secondary
door. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says even if you have four
doors
you're חייב במזוזה chayav bemezuza in one room.
As long as they don't all go from the same place.
I mean if it's just four doors from one room, then you
just... that might be, it might be correct that what Michael is
saying is, let's say there are four different ways to get into
the same room, right? They're not going to four different places. And
that's the question that the ראשונים Rishonim deal with of how to
make this גמרא Gemara work with רבי'ס Rebbe's little private door to
the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Why was that not חייב? chayav? Is
it because it was private as opposed to being the public general
use door? Or maybe it was different because of what you said,
that there the doors were all going into the same room. And
there you would say only the major door requires, not a minor
door. Okay, so there's ways of figuring out how to be, how
to fit this גמרא Gemara with the story about רבי. Rebbe.
The בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash didn't have any מזוזות mezuzot or not?
We're not required. Let's take a look. They had them. Okay, I
don't know. חייב בארבע מזוזות. chayav b'arba mezuzot. פשיטא, Pshita, the גמרא
Gemara says it's obvious. לא צריכא אע"ג דרגיל בחד, Lo tzricha af
al gav d'ragil b'chad, even though one is your most commonly used
one, ואתו v'atu the others are still חייב. chayav. So that again,
how does that fit with רבי Rebbe which it was exempt? Maybe
רבי Rebbe was again, so again I'll say what I said before,
רבי Rebbe could have been a case about private as opposed to,
you know, that was just for him. Or רבי Rebbe could have
been a case where there were multiple ways of getting into the
same room as opposed to different ways of getting into different rooms.
But this is, you know, as you might imagine, we'll just play
safe and put מזוזות mezuzot in every doorway. Okay, but here the
גמרא Gemara is sort of figuring that out.
Then do you make a ברכה bracha on that or?
Oh, that's a good question. Okay, I mean if it's the only
one you're putting, then maybe it falls into these categories maybe it...
Okay, אמר מימר: Amar Meimar: האי פיתחא דאקנא חייב במזוזה. Hai pitcha
d'Akarna chayeiv b'mezuzah. So this door of אקנא, Akarna, which is basically,
let's just see the רש"י Rashi here, בקרן זוית שויא ליה, bekeren
zavit shaveh lei, they had this like door like which was in
the corner of the house, they had a door shed. So that's
חייב chayeiv in a מזוזה. mezuzah. Probably because... so what it would
be? We'll see based on the question asked. אמר ליה רב אשי
למימר, Amar lei Rav Ashi le'Meimar, ולית ליה פצימין, ve'leite lei ptzimin,
it does not have, it does not have a doorframe. Okay, now
again what does that doorframe mean? For רש"י Rashi it might mean
an actual structure of a doorframe, for תוספות Tosafot it might mean
and this might be why it's in the corner, it's not shaped
like a door, right? Something that's basically a cut-out corner of the
house is not shaped like a classic doorway. It's like two walls
that just
combine,
it doesn't have even the shape of the doorway. So I mean
you could put up a doorframe and make it into a door
but you'd have to draw a line at an angle. Anyways, so
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה, Amar lei, אדי פצימי, Adai ptzimi,
which means alright so there are פצימי. ptzimi. So now what does
that mean? Okay, so it means we're assuming there are. Look at
רש"י, Rashi, אדי פצימי, Adai ptzimi, הרי, harei, so behold there are
פצימי. ptzimi. לומר אלו ראשי הכתלים הן הן פצימין. Lomar eilu rashei
ha'ktalim hen hen ptzimin. So we use the walls, even the unconnected
walls, as the doorframe. So yes, if this wall ends here and
this wall ends here and this sort of becomes an open space,
these are considered to be the frame of the door. What's interesting
is two things according to רש"י. Rashi. Number one is here we're
not talking about a separate structure, different from the רש"י Rashi we
saw before, just using the walls themselves. And number two, we're defining
a doorframe in a non-natural way where you don't have a naturally
shaped classic doorframe, just two perpendicular walls that are not meeting. Okay,
so all of this is important in terms of trying to figure
out exactly what defines a doorway.
Wait, I'm confused. So according to... so how would רש"י Rashi say
that when we said before, is this disagreeing based on the...
maybe, might be רש"י Rashi before was also לאו דווקא lav davka
and in principle agreed to תוספות. Tosafot. And when רש"י Rashi before
said it didn't have a lintel, maybe all he means is it
didn't have the shape of a lintel. I don't know, but רש"י
Rashi here is, at least רש"י Rashi here is saying both A:
you don't need a physical structure of a doorframe and B: to
even be in an unusual shape. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. רב פפא איקלע לבי מר שמואל. Rav Papa ikla l'bei Mar
Shmuel. רב פפא Rav Papa came to the house of מר שמואל.
Mar Shmuel. חזא ההוא פיתחא דלא הוה ליה אלא פצימא חד משמאלו.
Chaza hahu pitcha d'lo havei lei ela ptzima chad mismalo. He saw
that there was a certain door, door that only had a frame
on the left side. Okay, again it sounds like we're talking about
a physical structure of a frame. ועביד ליה מזוזה, Ve'avid lei mezuzah,
and he made a מזוזה mezuzah even though
it did not have a doorpost on both sides. So אמר ליה,
Amar lei, כמאן? keman? כרבי מאיר? K'Rabbi Meir? Who you going like?
Like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? We'll see the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
in a minute. אימא דאמר רבי מאיר מימין. Eima de'amar Rabbi Meir
mi'yamin. When did רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say that one doorpost is
enough? When it's the one on the right, which is the one
where you put the מזוזה. mezuzah. משמאל מי אמר? Mismol mi amar?
If your only doorpost is
on the left, he would never say you put a מזוזה. mezuzah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מי אמר? mi amar? To him... so
מאי היא? mai hi? What is this רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So
we don't know the response, but what is this רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir? דתניא: De'tanya: ביתך. beitecha. It says that you should put it
על מזוזות ביתך. al mezuzot beitecha. ביאתך, bi'atcha, the way you enter
in, famous דרשה, drasha, מן הימין, min hayamin, with the right. What
does that mean? We're assuming that people are righties, so therefore you
would step first with your right foot, right? I don't know if
you're aware of this that rightness, right-handedness is also footed... you have
people stand in line, you say take a step forward, and pretty
much everybody who's right-handed will move with their right foot and people
left-handed with their left foot. So anyway, so the way you go,
assuming right is dominant, is with your right, so therefore the מזוזה
mezuzah is on your right of the way you enter. There's a
question, what is considered the way you enter. We discussed before about
the flow of the doors and where the hinges are and so
on. But anyway, it's on the right of the way you enter.
מן הימין. Min hayamin. אתה אומר מן הימין או אינו אלא משמאל?
At amret min hayamin o eila mismol? Maybe it means even if...
even on the left? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ביתך. beitecha.
So it says ביתך. beitecha. מאי תלמודא? Mai talmuda? What do you
learn from that? So אמר רבה: Amar Rabbah: דרך ביאתך מן הימין.
derech bi'atcha min hayamin. It is the way you enter with is
with your... lead with your right. דכי עקר איניש כרעיה דימינא עקר.
De'ki akar inish krei d'yamina akar. When people lift up their foot,
they lift up their right foot. When you start walking, you'll walk
first with your right foot if you're a righty. Okay, רב שמואל...
Rav Shmuel... now we're still not... we're still yet to the רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir about the one doorpost. We're getting there. Yeah, should
you have a question?
If David were here, he
would ask a follow-up question.
Yes, and you're the stand-in David, go ahead. When does it change
from...
I imagine that what's written in the תורה Torah is: put a
מזוזה mezuzah on the entrance to your house. Right. And now we're
talking about the door to your house and formalizes it in a
door sense. So if it's a corner door, then it's not an
entrance, I
mean it's still an entrance. Well, the word מזוזה mezuzah does not
mean entrance, the word מזוזה mezuzah does mean like the frame, right?
על המזוזות ועל המשקוף, Al ha'mezuzot ve'al ha'mashkof, right? על שתי המזוזות
ועל המשקוף. Al shtei ha'mezuzot ve'al ha'mashkof.
It does mean sort of the... right, when it says by the
פסח, Pesach, the שתי המזוזות shtei ha'mezuzot are the two. So they
only had it one, or they had it in every single room
that's... that I said the first day we learned this, that it's
not so clear not only from the תורה Torah but from the
גמרא Gemara that you really require it in each room. Maybe it's...
maybe it's לאו דווקא lav davka for the whole house.
Although the גמרא Gemara does talk about going from room to room,
but the question
is... But
so but what's your point that the well I guess you're right,
actually the תורה Torah does say to
do that, right, right, right.
But that question of maybe ביתך, beitcha, maybe it's the מזוזה mezuzah
of your house doesn't mean every מזוזה mezuzah you have in your
house, maybe it means the one that's the basic one of the
house, the front door you know. So that's really the question, certainly
the way it was in פסח מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim, you know, they
didn't put the דם dam on every single room in the house.
Okay.
All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so now we
know the right, we're not done yet getting to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. ושמואל בר אחא, V'shmuel bar Achah, so where were we, ושמואל
בר אחא קמיה דרב פפא משמיה דרבא בר עולא אמר, V'shmuel bar
Achah k'mei d'Rav Pappa mishmei d'Rava bar Ulla amar,
so when שמואל בר אחא Shmuel bar Achah was in front of
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, he said the following: מהכא, meihacha, here's where
you learn it. ויקח יהוידע הכהן ארון אחד, V'yitkach Yehoyada haKohen aron
echad,
so he took this, this was also שקלים, Shkalim, right, so he
took this one box, ויקב חור
בדלתו, v'yikov chor b'dalto, so his first צדקה tzedakah box, he made
a hole in the top, ויתנו אתו אצל המזבח מימין, v'yiteinu oto
etzel hamizbei'ach miyamin, he put it by the altar on the right.
בבוא איש בית ה', b'vo ish beit Hashem, when a person would
come into the house of God, ונתנו שמה הכהנים שמרי הסף את
כל הכסף המובא בית ה', v'natnu sham hakohenim shomrei hasaf et kol
hakesef hamuva beit Hashem, and they would put there all the money
they collected. So what does that prove? It somehow, because it says
that when you come to the house of God בימין, biyamin, somehow
the idea of entry emphasizes the emphasis of the right. Okay. Back
to that now, back to our discussion, מאי רבי מאיר? mai Rabbi
Meir? Okay, that was all very nice that the idea of the
right, but where do you get the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir idea?
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, בית שאינו אלא פצים
אחד, bayit she'eino ella ptzim echad, if the house only has one
doorpost, רבי מאיר מחייב במזוזה וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi Meir mechayeiv b'mezuzah v'chachamim
potrin. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're חייב, chayav, חכמים chachamim say
you're פטור. patur. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir? מזוזת
מזוזות כתיב, mezuzat mezuzot ktiv,
although it's not you know they say that it's written מזוזות, mezuzot,
but it's not actually, right? It's not written with a ו. vav.
Is it written with an extra ו? vav? No.
No. So wait, what do you do with that? I don't know.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't always have
the exact same text that we had. They had extra חסירה ויתירה
chaseira v'yetira
as the גמרא gemara says explicitly at times.
Okay, מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר, mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir, what's the reasoning
of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? דתניא, d'tanya, מזוזות, mezuzot, שומע אני מיעוט
מזוזות שתים, shomei ani mi'ut mezuzot shtayim, maybe you need both doorposts,
maybe it means two.
We read it מזוזות, mezuzot, right? מזוזות ביתך. mezuzot beitecha.
Is it written with a ו? vav? Let me look at that.
I'm
assuming that this is accurately representing it.
Is it only in one place?
No, it's in both parts of
שמע.
Shema. Let's take a look.
Let's look in both.
Right, they're a bit complex.
Oh no, but here it says מזוזת כתיב. mezuzat ktiv. You have
to take out the ו. vav.
I know that it's written, I
know, let me take a look, hold on.
ואתחנן, V'etchanan, שמע ישראל, Shema Yisrael, על
מזוזות al mezuzot without a ו. vav. It's מזוזות mezuzot but without
a ו. vav. And in עקב Eikev it
is,
עקב Eikev it
is, excuse me,
in עקב Eikev it's with a
ו, vav, וכתבתם על מזוזות. u'chtavtam al mezuzot.
One's with and one's without. Okay, there you go, that's probably exactly
the פשט. pshat. Let's go back. Okay, so מאי טעמא דרבנן, mai
ta'ama d'rabbanan, why did the rabbis say you need both? So it
says מזוזות כתיב, mezuzot ktiv, actually so they should have written ו
ר מ ו vav-resh-mem-vav here because ו ר מ ו vav-resh-mem-vav is
the שמע Shema is without it anyway, one of them says plural
with a ו, vav, you need both. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר, mai
ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir, what's the reason of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? דתניא,
d'tanya, מזוזות mezuzot which is plural, שומע אני מיעוט מזוזות שתים, shomei
ani mi'ut mezuzot shtayim, maybe you need both doorposts. כשהוא אומר מזוזת,
k'shehu omer mezuzat, if
it should be בפרשה שניה b'parsha shniya or maybe מזוזות mezuzot because
here we're going to do a דרשה. drasha. Okay, anyway, שאין תלמוד
לומר, she'ein talmud lomar,
why does it again say the plural? הוי ריבוי אחר ריבוי, havei
ribui achar ribui, it's, you know, broadening after broadening. So this classic
rabbinic principle, ואין ריבוי אחר ריבוי אלא למעט, v'ein ribui achar ribui
ella lema'eit, and of course once it says two and then it
says two afterwards, it's really telling you you don't need to, even
one is enough. It's funny that it does not make the point
that in one of the places it says מזוזת mezuzat without the
ו. vav. So מיעטו
הכתוב למזוזה אחד, mi'ito hakatuv limzuzah achad, one מזוזה mezuzah is enough,
meaning one doorpost. בבי רבי ישמעאל, b'bei Rabbi Yishmael, that's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says explaining the position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
רבי עקיבא אומר אינו צריך, Rabbi Akiva omer eino tzarich, you don't
need that דרשה, drasha, כשהוא אומר על המשקוף ועל שתי המזוזות, k'shehu
omer al hamashkof v'al shtei hamuzuzot,
here we go, פסח מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim, on the lintel and on
the two מזוזות, mezuzot, שאין תלמוד לומר שתי, she'ein talmud lomar shtei,
why does it say two מזוזות? mezuzot? Why doesn't it say on
the מזוזות? mezuzot? So why does it say שתי? shtei? Why did
it have to say two? זה בנין אב, zeh binyan av, this
is a prototype. to the paradigm, כל מקום שנאמר מזוזות אינו אלא
אחת. kol makom shene'emar mezuzot eino ela achat. When it normally says
מזוזות, mezuzot, it means your מזוזות, mezuzot, meaning you know, not meaning
which however many you have, but it does not mean assuming a
doorframe of two. It really means even if there's only one. עד
שיפרט לך הכתוב שנים. ad sheyafrit lecha hakatuv shenayim. Until the Torah
says on your two מזוזות, mezuzot, then it's insisting that both be
present. So what we are saying is that he was astounded how
can you have a מזוזה mezuzah up even if you only have
one doorpost? I understand that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you only
need one doorpost, but presumably רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would require the
right doorpost where you're putting the מזוזה, mezuzah, not the left doorpost
and it was not a response to that. So from here we
also learn the idea that the מזוזה mezuzah goes on the right.
Again, what's interesting is the question about what is being defined as
doorpost. All of this idea that he had only one משקוף mashkof
makes it sound like we're talking about a physical structure of a
doorpost. We're not just saying that the other side was not somehow
also looking like it but it didn't have the physical structure. So
the question of whether a doorframe and doorpost require the physical structure
or whether they just require the shape of the wall from the
ceiling to be that way is again brought into question here. Here
it sounds like you need a physical structure. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, we're wrapping up
מזוזה. mezuzah. וכתבתם, uchtavtam, you shall write them, the מזוזה. mezuzah. יכול
יכתבנה על האבנים, yachol yichtevena al ha'avanim, which is what the Torah
sounds like. Get out your pen and write it literally on the
wall itself, on the מזוזה mezuzah itself. נאמר כאן כתיבה ונאמר להלן
כתיבה. ne'emar kan ktivah vene'emar lehalan ktivah. It says here write and
it says
later write. מה להלן על הספר, mah lehalan al hasefer, the same
way it says later on a book which is by a גט,
get, it says that you should write it וכתב לה ספר כריתות,
vechatav lah sefer keritut, so it's on some type of a ספר,
sefer, a book, a parchment.
וכתב לה ספר כריתות, vechatav lah sefer keritut, so מה להלן על
הספר. mah lehalan al hasefer. There's always a question when it says
להלן על הספר. lehalan al hasefer. רש״י Rashi says it means גט,
get, תוספות Tosafot says it means the פרשה parsha by סוטה. sotah.
Anyway, but there it does say ספר. sefer. אף כאן על הספר,
af kan al hasefer, here too on some type of a parchment
which is then affixed to the doorpost. או כלך לדרך זו, o
kalech lederech zo, or maybe try this one. נאמר כאן כתיבה ונאמר
להלן כתיבה. ne'emar kan ktivah vene'emar lehalan ktivah. It says here write,
it says there write. Where do you write? When you cross over
the ירדן, yarden, it says you shall write this entire, you know,
the ברכות והקללות, brachot vehaklallot, you shall write them על האבנים al
ha'avanim on the stones.
So right, that's by Gilgal and what was the other place? Okay,
anyway, so it says you write on the stones. ונאמר להלן כתיבה.
vene'emar lehalan ktivah. מה להלן על האבנים, mah lehalan al ha'avanim, the
same way there it's stone, אף כאן על האבנים, af kan al
ha'avanim, maybe here you write directly on the stone. נראה למי דומה,
nireh lemi domeh, let's see which one is it more similar to.
דנים כתיבה הנוהגת לדורות מכתיבה הנוהגת לדורות. danim ktivah hanohaget ledorot michtivah
hanohaget ledorot. You apply writing that applies to later generations whether it's
סוטה sotah or גט get to a מזוזה mezuzah which is a
מצוה mitzvah for future generations.
ואין דנים כתיבה הנוהגת לדורות מכתיבה שאינה נוהגת לדורות. ve'ein danim ktivah
hanohaget ledorot michtivah she'einah nohaget ledorot. And don't learn out from something
that does not apply for all generations, a one-time מצוה mitzvah of
writing on the stones. So כמו שנאמר להלן kemo shene'emar lehalan and
like and we also see later that the idea of writing means
על הקלף al haklaf because it says ויאמר להם ברוך vayomer lahem
baruch and Baruch said to them explaining how מגילת איכה megillat eichah
was written, מפיו יקרא אלי את הדברים, mipiv yikra elai et hadevarim,
Jeremiah would dictate to me ואני כותב על הספר בדיו, va'ani kotev
al hasefer bedyo, I would write on the parchment with ink. So
standard writing is on parchment with ink, it is not directly on
the stones. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar
leih rav acha breih derava lerav ashi, so what?
Would he be engraving?
Right, it would not be engraving, it would also not be writing
with ink on the stones. It would be writing on parchments. So
אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar leih rav acha
breih derava lerav ashi, so Rav Acha said to Rav Ashi, רחמנא
אמר על מזוזות, rachmana amar al mezuzot, ואת אמרת נילף כתיבה כתיבה.
ve'at amrat neilaf ktivah ktivah. Oh,
you gotta love it when the גמרא Gemara does that. Like, okay,
one minute, the Torah says explicitly write it on your doorpost and
you're telling me about some גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. I mean I
don't know why all of a sudden of all places here is
where he decided to be, you know, sort of astounded or offended,
but he's saying look the פסוק pasuk says write on your doorpost,
what are you telling me write on a קלף? klaf? So he
said that, okay, it's not just גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, it's actually
I can read it into the פסוק pasuk itself. אמר קרא, amar
kra, the פסוק pasuk says וכתבתם, uchtavtam, you shall write them. כתיבה
תמה, ktivah tamah, it should be a perfect writing. You can't write
well on stone. You can write well on קלף. klaf. So if
it says a perfect writing, that suggests not literally on the doorpost.
והדר vehadar and then it says, so first you get it nicely
written on קלף klaf and then על מזוזות, al mezuzot, then put
it on your מזוזות. mezuzot. So don't write it on the מזוזה,
mezuzah, write it and then put it on the
מזוזה. mezuzah. ומאחר דכתיב וכתבתם, ume'acher dechtiv uchtavtam, now that we're getting
it from וכתבתם, uchtavtam, האי גזירה שוה למה לי? hai gezerah shavah
lamah li? Why did I need the גזירה שוה? gezerah shavah? אי
לא גזירה שוה הוי אמינא ליכתב על אבנא ולקבעה אסיפא, i la
gezerah shavah havah amina lichtav al avna ulikbe'ah asipa, maybe I could
write it nicely if you know, if you have to write something
like standing up, like what it is, vertically, you can't, it's hard
to write. But maybe I could still get a nice writing if
I wrote it on a stone flat in my studio. I was
writing it on my stone and it was horizontal and then I
put the stone up in the door. So קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, not that way, that you have to write on קלף.
klaf. But again, it's quite fascinating that of all the things he's
offended that it doesn't go after the פשט, pshat, especially we're about
to turn to תפילין tfillin where it says, you know, וקשרתם ukeshartam
between your eyes, בין עיניך, bein einecha, where it's not literally בין
עיניך bein einecha and all these other types of things, but for
whatever reason that was the question and that was the answer he
gave. Now we turn to תפילין. tefillin. I really hope we get
through the דף daf I wanted to because we're getting to another
famous debate as you can imagine of רש״י Rashi רבנו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam. Let's take a look. ארבע פרשיות שבתפילין מעכבות זו את זו
ואפילו כתבן מעקבן. arba parshiyot she'batefillin m'akvot zu et zu v'afilu ktavan
m'akvan. You need all four פרשיות parshiyot of תפילין, tefillin, even one
letter wrong is a problem. פשיטא, pshita, obviously. So I don't know
why it's obvious, but okay, it's obvious to the גמרא Gemara that
even one letter is a problem. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
לא נצרכה אלא לקוצו של יוד. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav lo
nitzrecha ela l'kotzo shel yud. Exactly what we said before by the
מזוזה, mezuzah, even the little, you know, even the little thorn of
the יוד yud which is again either the left hand thing that
goes up or the right leg. The right leg is more obvious,
the left hand thing is just a, you would think it's just
a flourish, and nevertheless we need it. So the גמרא Gemara says
הא נמי פשיטא, ha nami pshita, that's also obvious. לא נצרכה אלא
לאידך דרב יהודה, Lo nitzrecha ela l'idach d'rav Yehuda, like the other
statement דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, d'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, he's
in the name of רב, כל אות שאין ריוח מוקף לה מארבע
רוחותיה פסולה. kol ot she'ein reivach mukaf la me'arba ruchoteha psula. Any
letter that is not מוקף גויל, mukaf gevil, does not have parchment
touching on all four sides, meaning it's connected to another letter, is
invalid. You need parchment surrounding every single letter. Okay, that was an
exact quote from the גמרא Gemara. we had before but the מזוזה.
mezuzah. Now we turn to specifically looking at תפילין. tefillin. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabbanan. So here we actually start from פסוקים, pesukim, which is
nice.
לטטפת לטטפת לטטפת, l'totafot l'totafot l'totafot, these should be for לטטפת. totafot.
How we're going to say how you know that there are four
בתים batim
and you know four פרשיות. parshiyot. הרי כאן ארבע דברי רבי ישמעאל.
harei kan arba divrei Rabbi Yishmael. So the two times it's written
without the וו, vav, once it's written with a וו, vav, and
that meets to four. תוספות Tosafot points out though that even the
one time it's written with a וו, vav, it's not the plural
וו. vav. It's not the וו vav that appears between the פא
peh and the תיו. taf. It's the וו vav that appears between
the two טיתין. tets. So that doesn't imply plural. So תוספות Tosafot
has a whole problem figuring that out. But whatever it is, and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns out that somehow that suggests four פרשיות.
parshiyot. Now רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, now you do realize of course
that the תורה Torah mentions תפילין tefillin four times. So you know
how much do we really need to learn it out from these
words. However, the other thing that we're learning out is not just
four פרשיות parshiyot but four compartments. The תפילין של ראש, tefillin shel
rosh, the תפילין של יד tefillin shel yad is לאות על ידך,
l'ot al yadecha, right? The תפילין של ראש tefillin shel rosh sometimes
is לזכרון l'zikaron and sometimes is לטטפת, l'totafot, and what we learn
out is that the תפילין של ראש tefillin shel rosh requires not
just all four פרשיות parshiyot but four separate compartments. And that might
also be what we are learning out by the words לטטפת. l'totafot.
That's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר אינו צריך.
Rabbi Akiva omer eino tzarich. You don't need to do that. כת
בקפטי שתים פט באפריקי שתים. kat d'kafti shtayim pat b'afriki shtayim. The
word טטפת totafot in certain languages is some hybrid of some languages,
which is pretty bizarre. אפריקי Afriki presumably is African, I have no
idea what קפטי Kafti is. But anyway, קפטה, Kapte, no, קצה. Katze.
No, the letters are wrong. Anyway,
but somehow the word means four. Now it's a good question, what
the heck does the word טטפת totafot mean? Does it mean amulet,
memory, what does it mean? So just quickly if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, לטטפת, l'totafot, the second תוספות, Tosafot, does a very unusual
thing, a little commentary not really dealing with a problem in the
גמרא. Gemara נראה דלשון טטפת הוא הראש אצל המצח. nireh d'lashon totafet
hu harosh etzel hamezach. So that may actually refer to the place
in the head where we put the תפילין, tefillin, above the forehead.
כמו טטפת ושרביטין כדאמר בפרק במה אשה. k'mo totafet v'sarbiten k'rafe mihei
isha. So he tries to bring a proof to that. And then
he has another interesting thing. He says אינמי, inami, like about five
lines in, נקראו טטפת על שם שהם בראש בין העינים לשון הבטה.
nikru totafot al shem shehem berosh bein ha'einayim lashon habata. Maybe the
word טטפת totafot in the Aramaic means to look and to see,
and he sort of says like the סית, sit, which means like
להציץ l'hatzit means to look. So it's actually very interesting right that
ציץ tzitz and the תפילין tefillin are God's name on your head.
There's a lot of comparison between ציץ, tzitz, so he says the
word ציץ tzitz means to see and the תפילין tefillin means לטטפת,
l'totafot, he says maybe also an Aramaic word comes from Aramaic derivation
of to see. Now what are we seeing? So you might say
that maybe it makes us think about God, look at the world
through a God lens. תוספות Tosafot actually then shifts and says no
it's what other people see. וראו כל עמי הארץ כי שם ה'
נקרא עליך. v'ra'u kol amei ha'aretz ki shem Hashem nikra alecha. You
know the famous דרשה, drasha, if people see you're wearing תפילין tefillin
and that sort of instills almost a sense of fear of God
that other people are seeing you wear תפילין. tefillin. But it is
interesting he compares it to ציץ tzitz and he says that the
word might have
to have to do with what do you call it, with seeing
or being seen. Now the question is also what does the word
תפילין tefillin mean? Because תפילין tefillin doesn't appear in the תורה Torah
anywhere. תפילין tefillin is a rabbinic word. And the singular of תפילין
tefillin is actually תפילה, tefilla, prayer. So what does it mean that
we're calling our תפילין tefillin prayer? Maybe because they're worn during prayer,
but actually in the time of the גמרא Gemara תפילין tefillin were
worn the whole day. So תוספות Tosafot gives a very bizarre, I
mean bizarre because you know we would never have thought of it,
explanation to what the word תפילין tefillin means. If you look later
in this תוספות Tosafot where he says it's like about two-thirds down
the line says the word וריסי עיניו v'reesei einav and then he
says ותפילין, u'tefillin, what does the word תפילין tefillin mean? נראה לשון
ויכוח. nireh lashon vikuach. It means like to justify yourself, to argue
and justify. כמו ויתפלל שעשה פלילות עם קונו, k'mo vayitpalel she'asa plilot
im kono, right? פלילים, plilim, the thing you know can mean to
sort of argue in front of a court. And what does that
mean? על שם שהם עדות והוכחה ששם ה' נקרא עליך ויראו
ממנו. al shem shehem eidus v'hochacha she'shem nikra alecha v'yire'u mimenu. Like
we wear it as testimony that God has chosen us and it's
sort of like again it's. Playing into this דרשה *drasha* of וראו
כל עמי הארץ *v'rau kol amei ha'aretz*. All the nations see that
you're wearing these תפילין tefillin, *tfillin* and then ויראו ממך *v'yiru mimeka*.
So while we look very bizarre when we wear תפילין Tefillin *tfillin*,
in a certain way you can turn that into a point of
pride. This is exactly because God has chosen us and this proves
that we are, we have received the תורה *Torah*. So it's interesting
that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the word טוטפת *Totafot* and תפילין Tefillin.
*tfillin* must tie both into that theme of being seen and sort
of being very distinctive. Okay. Yes.
The point of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*.
He's saying, through different languages, we learn out four, right? Because in
African it's two and something else is also two. So according to
that theory, the תורה *Torah* is using
words that have etymologies from two different languages. Right. So I don't
know if he thinks the תורה *Torah* created a new word. What
he might be saying is that this is a word that has
its etymology in other languages. It's a weird word. It means a
four-compartment chamber and its etymology comes from two other languages.
In one language it means two and in another language it means
two.
Right. I think he's saying that the תורה *Torah* is using a
word that has this etymology. But it is using words from some
other languages. Right. Right. It's not creating a new word. Just because
we don't know what the word means doesn't mean that the תורה
*Torah* created it. It doesn't mean it didn't have an acknowledged meaning
at the time.
It's not like a riddle. It's not so unclear. It makes הלכה
halacha *halacha*. Right. Exactly.
Well, no, it's very clear that they had the הלכה *halacha*, they
had the tradition. The question is that they now had to figure
out how to get it from the פסוק *pasuk*. That's very clear
of what's going on here. Okay. Now let's go back. תנו רבנן
Tanu rabbanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*. יכול יכתבם על ארבע עורות ויניחם בארבע בתים
Batim כארבע עורות *Yachol yichtivem al arba orot v'yanicham b'arba batim k'arba
orot*. So maybe you should put them in four separate compartments, meaning
write them on four separate parchments and put them in four separate
compartments. Now we do put them in four separate compartments, but it
means four unattached compartments, right? Maybe each compartment is separate and then
maybe they're all sewn together afterwards or something. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*,
ולזכרון בין עיניך *ul'zikaron bein einecha*. In one פסוק *pasuk* it does
not refer to it as טוטפות *Totafot* but זכרון *zikaron*. זכרון אחד
אמרתי לך ולא שנים וג' זכרונות *Zikaron echad amarti lach v'lo shnayim
v'gimmel zichronot*. It has to be one unit, not separate units. הכיצד
*Hakeitzad*? How do you do this? כותבן על ארבע עורות *Kotvan al
arba orot*. You write it on four קלפים klafim. *klafim*, the four
פרשיות Parshiot *parshiyot*. ומניחם בארבע בתים בעור אחד *Umanicham b'arba batim b'or
echad*. And you put them in four בתים *batim* constructed out of
one piece of leather. So Joe has a like picture here if
I may from the article, right? So it's the one piece of
leather that you create four compartments into. Can people more or less
see this picture? It's like imagine you've got a cloth and you
stick four, you make four compartments in it, but it's all structured
constructed out of a single piece of leather. So it's four compartments
but one unit, one object. Okay. בעור אחד *B'or echad*. אם כתבן
בעור אחד והניחן בארבע בתים יצא yatza, *Im katvan b'or echad v'hinichan
b'arba batim yatza*. Now
if you wrote it all on one parchment and got it into
four בתים *batim* you are יוצא yotze, *yotzei*. How the heck do
you write it on one parchment and put it into four בתים
*batim*? And I will tell you. רש"י *Rashi* says how. This is
what you do.
This is your one parchment, okay? This is your one parchment. You
write the four פרשיות Parshiot *parshiyot* down like this, like vertically. And
then you
do
this.
Here are my four פרשיות *parshiyot* of תפילין Tefillin. *tfillin*. They're all
going to, each one is going to sort of fit into a
separate בית bayit, *bayit*, right? You got it? And I'm sticking them
up and they're all on one piece of parchment connected at the
bottom. Okay.
Well, you could double up the parchment.
You could do that too. But that would, but anyway this way
sort of it's more, a little more stable this way than stretching
the parchment from בית bayit, *bayit* to בית bayit, *bayit*. Okay. So
maybe, so it says if I do that, believe it or not
I'm יוצא yotze *yotzei*. Why not? I mean, the parchment should be
no worse than the actual, than the actual תפילין *tfillin* itself, the
בית *bayit*, the structure itself which is four compartments all combined in
one. So maybe I can do the same here with the parchment.
So יצא *yatza*. You are יוצא *yotzei*. וצריך שיהא ריוח ביניהם *V'tzarich
sheyehei revach beineihem*. But you have to obviously leave some space between
the columns so you can do this, so you can tear them
vertically and do this. דברי רבי *Divrei Rabbi*. That's what רבי *Rabbi*
says. וחכמים אומרים *V'chachamim omrim*, אינו צריך eino tzarich. *eino tzarich*. You
don't need, which is pretty surprising. You don't need what? Any space
between them?
It's not exactly clear how the חכמים *Chachamim* here are imagining what
you would do. How you could get all four in without any
space between them. Nevertheless, ושוין שנותן חוט או משיכה בין כל אחת
ואחת *v'shavin shenotein chut o meshicha bein kol achat v'achat*. That you
also have to put a string or a mshicha between each one,
between each of the compartments. So the way, I don't know if
they have a picture of it, let me see. No,
they have a picture of the חריצים *charitzim*, of the grooves.
Yeah, I don't know.
They don't have a picture.
Okay, but they need to have somehow these compartments have to have
a string. string that basically sews them and tightens them together even
though they're all of one
hide, and אם אין חריצה ניכר, if their carvings, meaning the lines
between them is not obvious, פסולות. psulot. So if the compartment only
exists interior and you can't at the outside see, you know, if
you look at a תפילין, you see, I mean everything is done
exactly perfectly because we have these amazing machines, but anyway, you know,
you see these nice perpendicular lines and these four little slices and
you can see from the outside that it's four compartments held together.
But if you could not see from the outside and there were
only interior compartments, it would not be valid. Okay, so now it
goes on. תנו רבנן, כיצד כותבן, keitzad kotvan, how do you write
them? תפילין של יד, Tefillin shel yad, כותב על עור אחד, kotev
al or echad, you write it on one parchment. ואם כתב בארבעה
עורות והניח בבית אחד, ve'im katav be'arba'ah orot vehiniach bevayit echad, יצא,
but if you wrote it on four parchments and you put it
in one בית, you're יוצא, וצריך לדבק, vetzarich ledabek, but you would
have to glue the parchments together. שנאמר, Shene'emar, והיה לך לאות על
ידך, vehayah lecha le'ot al yadecha, it should be a singular אות
ot on your hand, and therefore you have to in the end
make it one even though you can start off with four pieces.
כשם שאות אחת מבחוץ כך אות אחת מבפנים, Keshem she'ot achat mibachutz
kach ot achat mibifnim, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehudah. So Rabbi
Yehudah says it also has to be one compartment, one unit, the
same way the של ראש shel rosh has four compartments, the של
יד shel yad has one, so the same way it's one, it
has to be one parchment, but you can start with four and
glue them together. That's what Rabbi Yehudah says. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi
Yosei omer, אינו צריך. Rabbi Yosei says you do not need to
glue them together, you can actually have four separate parchments inside your
של יד. shel yad. Pretty amazing. But now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, so Rabbi Yosei says, ומודה
לי רבי יהודה, umodeh li Rabbi Yehudah, Rabbi Yehudah would agree to
me, רבי יהודה ברבי, Rabbi Yehudah Berabbi, שאם אין לו she'im ein
lo תפילין של יד, tefillin shel yad, let's say you don't have
your shel yad, and you have, ויש לו שתי תפילין של ראש,
veyesh lo shtei tefillin shel rosh, let's say you don't have your
shel yad but somehow there's an extra shel rosh, what can you
do?
שתולה עור על אחת מהן ומניחה, shetoleh or al achat mehen uminichah,
that you take your shel rosh, you actually take a little piece
of leather, you stretch it over your shel rosh so at the
outside it looks like only one box. It's pretty interesting that here
we care about what it looks like on the outside, you know,
even a little bit more than what's reality on the inside. On
the inside it's four separate compartments, but you stretch the piece of
leather over it so it looks like it's one compartment. Okay, and
now he's saying you can be יוצא your shel yad with it.
What's your concern? It's four boxes, not one? No, it looks like
one box because you stretched the עור or on. What's... it's four
pieces of parchment on the inside. Four separate parchments on the inside
are okay with your shel yad. Okay, and he was so, שאם
אין לו she'im ein lo תפילין של יד, tefillin shel yad, ויש
לו שתי תפילין של ראש, veyesh lo shtei tefillin shel rosh, שתולה
עור על אחת מהן ומניחה. shetoleh or al achat mehen uminichah. גמרא
Gemara says, מודה היינו פלוגתייהו, modeh hayinu plugtaiyhu, what do you mean
he would agree? That's exactly their debate, that Rabbi Yehudah says four
pieces of parchment are not good, you need only one parchment. So
אמר רבא, מדבריו של רבי יוסי Amar Rava midvarav shel Rabbi Yosei,
חזר בו רבי יהודה. We can infer from Rabbi Yosei's since he
said Rabbi Yehudah would agree to me, that Rabbi Yehudah in the
end retracted his position. In the end, Rabbi Yehudah would agree that
you could have four separate parchments on the shel yad. So you
actually have a quite amazing thing, things that we never knew. The
shel rosh which is four compartments, which we know, have to look
like four compartments on the outside, so what it looks like on
the outside is very important, and the flip is true about the
shel yad. And what we actually see is you don't need four
separate parchment, you can actually have one parchment that goes into each
of the compartments and that would be enough. That's the shel rosh.
The shel yad, which we know is one compartment, we're learning a
couple of things: on the one hand it can actually be four
compartment on the inside if you put a single skin on the
outside, how you can convert a shel rosh into a shel yad,
and the other thing is that we're now saying that you don't
even need one קלף, klaf, in theory you could have four separate
קלפים. klafim, So it's quite interesting the amount of variation that we're
allowed here that I don't think we would have expected. And now
the גמרא Gemara just ends and we'll end with this.
אמר רבא Amar Rava, מדבריו של רבי יוסי, oh sorry, גמרא Gemara
says, איני, eini, could you really use your shel rosh as a
shel yad? והשלח רבי חנינא משמיה דרבי יוחנן, vehashlach Rabbi Chanina mishmei
d'Rabbi Yochanan, תפילין של יד עושה אותה של ראש, tefillin shel yad
oseh otah shel rosh, you can convert a shel yad into a
shel rosh, at least you can use the parchment, you have to
convert the
בית, ושל ראש אין עושה אותה של יד, veshel rosh ein oseh
otah shel yad, but you cannot use a shel rosh into a
shel yad. Why not? For the old reason, לפי שאין מורידין מקדושה
חמורה לקדושה קלה, lefi she'ein moridin mikedushah chamurah likedushah kalah, because the
shel rosh is considered a higher קדושה. kedushah. Number one, we'll talk
about that later, but it's higher up on the body, and whatever,
the shel rosh, and the other real reason is because the shel
rosh has two-thirds of God's name written on the actual box itself.
You have the שין, shin, right, on the actual box, and you
have the דלת dalet formed by the knot, and the shel yad
only has a יוד yod formed by a knot. So the shel
rosh is considered holier because it has two-thirds of God's name, you
know, not just on the parchment but on the box. So you
cannot go from the shel rosh into a shel yad. So how
here did we say just, you know, take a piece of leather
on top of it? You know, and so we've been talking about
the structure of the בית, how many קלפים, Klafim but the problem
is it's a higher
קדושה. kedushah. Right, and if you're just using not the—you never had
the strap on at all yet.
Well, you might have had it on and now you're redoing it.
Right. So it is true that although we say that it's because
of the strap, that we generally assume that the קדושה, Kedusha, you
know, sort of relates to the thing even when you—even without the
strap. But it's a good point. Okay, we'll see later about the
idea of the של ראש Shel Rosh having a higher קדושה. Kedusha.
Let's just see the answer. The גמרא's Gemara answer is לא קשיא.
Lo Kashya. Did I read
the—לא קשיא, Lo Kashya, הא בעתיקתא הא בחדתא, Ha b'atikta ha b'chadta,
new or old. What does that mean? If you have never used
your תפילין yet, even if you've made it into a של ראש,
Shel Rosh, it does not yet have the הלכה status of a
של ראש Shel Rosh until it's used as such. Okay, so therefore
we're talking here that you can convert it before you've actually put
it to use. So again, it's not just the physical reality that
it has these letters, it does have to do with being designated
as a של ראש, Shel Rosh, used as a של ראש. Shel
Rosh. So we'll see more later about why the של ראש Shel
Rosh has a higher קדושה. Kedusha. So that's one answer. ולמאן דאמר
הזמנה מילתא, U'le-man d'amar hazmana milta, now there's a debate in the
גמרא Gemara whether does something get its status when it's been designated,
which is הזמנה, hazmana, or does it actually have to be used?
So according to the opinion that the status comes from the moment
of designation, why can you use your של ראש Shel Rosh for
your של יד? Shel Yad? As soon as it's designated, it has
the status of a של ראש Shel Rosh and it can't be
lower קדושה. Kedusha. So the גמרא says, הזמנה מילתא דאתני עלה מעיקרא.
Hazmana milta d'atni ala me'ikara. Before you actually—הזמנה hazmana you have to
designate. So if at the time that I'm making it, I'm saying
from the very outset, "Oh, if I need to I want to
convert this to a של יד," Shel Yad, then you're allowed to
convert it, it does not yet have its status. Okay, so how
do you get it that you can use a של ראש Shel
Rosh for של יד? Shel Yad? What about going down in קדושה?
Kedusha? So we either say it was never used, so it didn't
have the status, and even those that say it doesn't have to
be used and say that designation is enough to give it its
status, maybe it wasn't designated. Maybe it was—you stipulated from the very
beginning that you could change it. So we're going to end here
because I don't want to—because we're already overtime and the next two
lines are the famous debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות about רש״י
Rashi and רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam about the order of the פרשיות
in the תפילין. But what we have learned is some quite fascinating
things about number one, yet the של ראש Shel Rosh requires four
separate בתים out of one עור. Or. But even the קלפים Klafim
actually do not have to be separate. They can be in some
degree combined. And we also found very interestingly that the של יד,
Shel Yad, there's an opinion that you can have separate קלפים and
you can actually have separate compartments as long as on the top
of it, it all looks like one if you stretch a piece
of leather. So greater variation than we're normally used to finding, and
we will turn tomorrow to—start tomorrow with the very famous debate of
רש״י Rashi and רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam of the basic order of
the פרשיות in the
תפילין.